So today's דף daf is ס"ב, samech bais, sixty-two, and we pick
up at the very top. And we had just started a new
פרק, perek, where now we are, sorry, one second, thank you so
much.
That's actually relating to the דף daf here.
Okay,
that's for יבמות. Yevamos.
Yeah, I guess so. Anyway, we will pick up with the גמרא,
Gemara, the new פרק perek here deals with עירוב חצרות Eruv Chatzeros
moving from בתי חצרות Batei Chatzeros from עירוב תחומין Eruv Techumin
and deals with a the full fascinating issue of who can participate,
who makes it a problematic, and their whole sense of essentially community
which is being created through the עירוב חצרות. Eruv Chatzeros. And the
first point of the משנה Mishnah was was that if a non-Jew
or somebody who did not agree to עירוב, Eruv, believe in it,
meaning a כותי Kuti or צדוקי, Tzaduki, we'll see if there's a
difference, then they create a problem, they make the courtyard forbidden to
you, and the משנה Mishnah does not even tell you how you
might want to solve that problem, but they cannot participate in the
עירוב Eruv and their presence creates problems. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Top of ס"ב עמוד א'. samech bais amud aleph.
יתיב אביי בר אבין, Yasiv Abaye bar Avin, so אביי בר אבין
Abaye bar Avin was sitting, ורב חנינא בר אבין, ve-Rav Chanina bar
Avin, and רב חנינא בר אבין, Rav Chanina bar Avin, brothers, ויתיב
אביי גבייהו, ve-yasiv Abaye gabaihu, and אביי Abaye was sitting next to
them, ויתבי וקאמרי, ve-yasvi ve-ka-amri, and they were sitting and saying, בשלמא
bishlama רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir קסבר, kasavar, so I get רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir because now what they're dealing with is that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says even one of these people make a problem, I'm
sorry, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said that these people are always a
problem, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's only a problem if
there are two or more Jews in the courtyard, but if there's
only one Jew in the courtyard they're not a problem at all,
which basically means you can have one Jew, ten non-Jews or ten
כותים Kutim or צדוקים, Tzadukim,
and he can carry in the courtyard and carry from the courtyard
to his house, his house to the courtyard, the courtyard to their
houses, even though there's no עירוב, Eruv, even though there's a lot
of other people using that space.
But that is only
with
one Jew, two Jews already it's a problem. So let's take a
look. בשלמא bishlama רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we get רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir who says doesn't matter one or two Jews, קסבר דירת עובד
כוכבים שמה דירה, kasavar diras akum shema dira, his present, his domicile
counts as a domicile, so it's as if that, you know, it's
considered that there's some other presence in this courtyard, and if it's
not a unified, he's not part of the community, it's not a
unified domain, it's a problem. ולא שנא חד ולא שנא תרי, Velo
shna chad velo shna terei, doesn't matter one Jew or two Jews.
אלא Ela
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, מאי קסבר, mai kasavar,
what does רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hold? אי
קסבר דירת עובד כוכבים שמה דירה, I kasavar diras akum shema dira,
if he holds that the domicile of the non-Jew is a domicile,
so his presence makes a difference and impacts the situation, then אפילו
חד נמי ניסר, afilu chad nami nitzur, then even with one Jew
it should be a problem. You have other presence in the courtyard,
you want to carry and there are other people
who have a domain and have rights in the courtyard. ואי לא
שמה דירה, Ve-i lo shema dira, and if the domicile of a
non-Jew is not considered a domicile for these purposes, you know, he's
not part of the Jewish community, if you conceive of it that
way, then אפילו תרי נמי לא ניסר, afilu terei nami lo nitzur,
then two shouldn't make it, even with two it shouldn't be a
problem, make up your mind, what does the difference one Jew or
two Jews matters? If you say the non-Jew is not relevant, fine,
he's not relevant. If he is relevant, then he should always be
relevant.
אמר להו אביי, amar lehu Abaye, so אביי Abaye said to them,
these two sons of רב אבין, Rav Avin,
וסבר רבי מאיר שדירת עובד כוכבים שמה דירה, ve-savar Rabbi Meir she-diras
akum shema dira, he says wait, wait, wait, I don't even agree
with your assumption of what worked for you in the משנה. Mishnah.
You assumed that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says whether one Jew
or two Jews it's always a problem is because fundamentally the domicile
of a non-Jew is a domicile, his presence in the courtyard is
noted and a factor and problematic, and it's like a different domain
in the courtyard. Says since when is that true? That that's really
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir principled position. והתניא, Ve-ha tanya, it's just like
a Jew, right? You answer a question with another question. But by
answering with this other question it's going to come back to be
the answer to their question. Says first I want to show you
that I disagree with your assumption, even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
has a problem regardless is not because he says that their domicile
is considered like a domicile, why? והתניא, Ve-ha tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא Baraisa and we're going to quote this at the bottom
of the דף, daf, חצרו של עובד כוכבים הרי היא כדיר של
בהמה, Chatzeros shel oved kochavim harei hu ke-diras shel beheimah, so that
obviously is a deeply disturbing statement, the courtyard or the of the
non-Jew, the house and the presence of, you know, and the yard
of the non-Jew is like a stable. So, right, so I looked
at Steinsaltz out of curiosity and he sort of said, well, all
this means is is that it's not relevant for halachic purposes. Okay,
nevertheless, you know, it's still obviously a very disturbing metaphor, and you
know, and there are other statements in the גמרא Gemara about attitudes
towards non-Jews, you know, that make that make you wonder if it's
just, you know, a throwaway line or not. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara does say here that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of
that there's a statement in the ברייתא Baraisa which we're going to
see later, is part of a statement of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
which basically says... Their presence has no effect. It's not like another
person is living in the courtyard for these purposes, and if you
wanted to sort of tone down the metaphor here, the point being
since they're not part of the Jewish community, therefore it's completely irrelevant
for our idea of establishing that sense of about whether it's considered
a unified courtyard or not. So their presence is irrelevant. And nevertheless,
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir still says that they make a problem. So
how do you have it both ways? How do you say if
they have a domicile or it's not like they have a domicile,
and nevertheless, it's a problem and you can't carry? So what's going
on there? So the point is it's not a principled problem, it's
a גזירה gezeira problem, it's a תקנה takkanah problem. Let's take a
look.
אלא אמר אביי Ella amar Abaye דכולי עלמא דירת עכו"ם לא שמה
דירה. de-kulei alma dirat akum lo shemeih dirah. Everybody agrees that a
non-Jew's presence in the courtyard, domicile is not a domicile. It's not
relevant for these הלכות. halachot. It's like he's not there.
הכא hecha בגזירה be-gezeira שמא ילמדו ממעשיו shema yilmedu mima'asav קמיפלגי. kamiflegi.
The whole issue of the non-Jew being a problem in the courtyard
and having
to, that he makes it forbidden and are there ways around it
and so on is only because the Rabbis didn't want you living
with non-Jews. And therefore they made it much more difficult for you
to make an עירוב eruv with non-Jews being present. Now that's quite
interesting because it's only impact on שבת?
Shabbat? What about the rest of the week?
Well, okay, it's like that point I said the other time: they
won't listen to me during the rest of the week. But okay,
so you make a difficulty on שבת Shabbos and it makes a
and it's a counter-incentive. Now, okay, is that really what's going on
in the משנה Mishnah or not is hard to know. This is
at least what the גמרא Gemara is speculating, although again רבי אליעזר'ס
Rebbe Eliezer's position in the משנה Mishnah is very strange. I mean,
because why is two Jews more of a problem than one Jew?
So we're going to see how the גמרא Gemara is going to
make sense of that given this explanation. But I should point out,
and I again mentioned that שרלוט פונרוברט Charlotte Fonrobert has an article
about עירובין eruvin which primarily deals with a lot with like this
discussion, the concept of unifying the courtyard, not so much the architecture
but this concept of coming together and community and so on, which
is,
that the realities of עירוב eruv in terms of what they do
to define a coherent Jewish
community are used even until
today. That you first of all you make an עירוב, eruv, so
then first of all, the property values non-Jews don't want it because
then it's all these Orthodox Jews are going to move in, I
shouldn't say it's always non-Jews, but whatever, it changes the nature of
the community. Property values go up because then more Orthodox Jews can
move in. There's all of this dynamics that come
about. And the issue is is that if the concept of the
עירוב eruv is to create this like coherent sense of a courtyard,
that's all very nice if you live in your nice little small
Jewish village. But if you're living in a cosmopolitan city that fundamentally
you're a minority,
so there's
like almost like a paradigm shift or like a trying to conceptualize
this as a Jewish courtyard when you're a minority in somebody
else's space, it really creates a certain type of a conflict in
terms of the model. So here what you see, it's actually interesting,
the whole idea of עירוב eruv creates this coherent unified Jewish community
and the way the גמרא Gemara is explaining what's going on in
the משנה Mishnah is is that we want you therefore to avoid
a more mixed community and we're sort of doing it through this
vehicle of עירובין. eruvin. So we're going to make it more difficult
for you to carry in your courtyard on שבת Shabbos if you're
living among
non-Jews. And that's consistent with the whole idea that what עירובין eruvin
does is it creates for a greater
coherence within the courtyard of the Jewish community, yes.
I noticed that when I was visiting Paris two years ago, there's
no עירוב eruv and Jews are spread all over the city, there's
not
an identifiable Jewish area anymore, and there used to be before World
War II when there was an עירוב. eruv.
Right, so that's really it. The עירוב eruv really creates a reality.
If it creates a space you can carry on שבת Shabbos then
it sort of brings all Jews together in that space. And people
want to carry on שבת, Shabbos, which is why when there's an
עירוב eruv everybody comes together. So thinking about that, about the
real-world impact it has about creating a community and a dense and
coherent community, so it's saying so we don't want it to be
a mixed community, so we're going to make it harder to make
an עירוב. eruv. Okay, so let's take a look. Don't worry, the
גמרא'ס Gemara's thought about that. So let's take a look. Okay, so
he says in principle the non-Jew shouldn't be an issue. We just
are going to say that you're not going to be able to
do it because we want you not to be living with the
non-Jew. Which by the way explains why the משנה Mishnah doesn't even
have a solution. I've mentioned to you the idea of rental, but
that's not even in the משנה, Mishnah, right? So the משנה Mishnah
maybe according to maybe the משנה Mishnah didn't give you any option
to make an עירוב eruv if you're living with non-Jews. Okay, the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say you could rent, but let's take a
look. So קמיפלגי. kamiflegi. רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב סבר Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov savar כיון דאכל עמך kivan de-oichal
imcha חשוד אשפיכות דמים. chashud ashfichut damim. This is based on גמרא,
Gemara, משנת mishnas and... גמרות Gemaras in עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, which
could have been very true at the time that the משנה Mishnah
was being written when they were subject to Roman persecution. So they
were concerned that non-Jews
would, and we know sadly it was true at various times in
Jewish history, and of course not always, but anyway, there were times
when they were very concerned about their non-Jewish neighbors that they might
have murderous
intention. So therefore since you know that,
so תרי דשכיחי דדיירי trei d'shchichi d'dayri so two people might, two
Jews might choose to live in the same courtyard with non-Jews. At
least there's two of them they wouldn't be afraid
that something could happen. So therefore that's a possible scenario. גזרו בהו.
gazru behu. So therefore the rabbis did say that's going to be
a problem. חד לא שכיח, chad lo shchiach, so this is quite
ironic, right? One, that it's very rare that that would ever happen.
What one Jew is going to live amongst a whole courtyard of
non-Jews? So לא גזרו ביה רבנן. lo gazru bay rabbanan. So they
didn't make it a problem because the whole point here was like
a sort of social policy and they wanted to prevent people living,
but the case, they didn't feel they needed to make a גזירה
gezeira by one. So therefore you have one Jew living amongst non-Jews
he can carry. As soon as there are two, oh, that's already
a problem. Now we have to say you can't carry. Again it's
very, very strange because it's just why bother making the distinction, like
you have to go out of your way to distinguish between those
cases and you're almost sending a signal, almost, which is according to
the way the גמרא Gemara understands it counterproductive. The signal you're sending
is it's okay for one of
you to live in such a courtyard but not two of you.
So it's a very strange explanation. The position of רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is very hard to understand.
You should have said majority, like say there's ninety-nine of you and
one of him, he's אסור assur on everyone else?
Right, it's a good
point. Anyway, but what's more interesting, although I admit that רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב's Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov position is still quite challenging, is
that the גמרא Gemara understands that this is fundamentally
a תקנה takkana idea, a policy issue about creating a coherent Jewish
community separate from the non-Jewish community. And again thinking about how that
plays out nowadays, not that it's separate but what it does to
solidify the Jewish community within the bounds of the עירוב eruv and
there's clear parallels. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So that's
how he explained what's going on in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי מאיר
סבר, Rabbi Meir savar, now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds, why wouldn't
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, why does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir think even
one is an issue? No, זמנין דמיקרי
ודיירי. zimnin d'mikri v'dayri. Sometimes it happens, sometimes you'll have one Jew
amongst them and
we want to make that a problem too.
Now זמנין, zimnin, there are times, דמיקרי d'mikri it happens, ודיירי v'dayri
and you live among them, even one among many. ואמרו רבנן, v'amru
rabbanan, the rabbis say, אין עירוב מועיל במקום עובד כוכבים. ein eruv
mo'il bimkom oved kochavim.
So therefore they said we want to make you this case not
happen. So we're going to say the עירוב eruv is not going
to work if there are non-Jews there, even though like again in
principle their domicile shouldn't be relevant. ואין ביטול רשות מועיל במקום עובד
כוכבים. v'ein bitul reshush mo'il bimkom oved kochavim.
Now we haven't mentioned that either but it was sort of implicit
at the end of the משנה Mishnah about the story with the
צדוקי. Tzedoki. So there may be cases like a צדוקי Tzedoki and
a כותי Kuti that we allow you this idea of ביטול רשות
bitul reshus
of them to waive their rights, but again the point here is
to make it difficult. So if we're trying to make it difficult
we're going to say even waiving of the rights isn't going to
work. Now again, according to the משנה Mishnah you could have said
nothing works. The משנה Mishnah doesn't give you a solution if a
non-Jew is there. The גמרא's Gemara going to introduce a solution but
still explain why it's a difficult solution.
עד שישכיר, ad sheyaskir, the only thing that will work is you
have to rent. Now why is that going to make you want
to avoid living with them? So you could just say because you
don't want to have to pay rent every שבת. Shabbos. But the
גמרא Gemara goes even further than that. ועובד כוכבים לא מוגר, v'oved
kochavim lo mugar, and the non-Jew won't want to rent to you.
Why will he not want to rent to you? מאי טעמא? mai
taama? What's the
reason? אי נימא משום דסבר דילמא אתי לאחזוקי ברשותו, ei neima mishum
d'savar dilma ati l'achzukei b'reshuso, maybe he's afraid if he rents to
you every שבת, Shabbos, you're going to come to
claim real rights on the courtyard. It won't just be some formal
ritual thing. You're going to say hey, you rented it to me,
I'm sorry, you have no rights in the courtyard anymore, not just
on שבת Shabbos and even the rest of the week, or maybe
you won't and carry on שבת. Shabbos. So if he's afraid that
you're really going to exercise serious rights and therefore he won't want
to rent. הניחא למאן דאמר שכירות בריאה בעינן. haniicha l'man d'amar schirus
bria beinun. That's good if you say you need a healthy rental,
interesting phrase. אלא למאן דאמר שכירות רעועה בעינן, ela l'man d'amar schirus
reu'a beinun, but if all you need is a shaky rental, מאי
איכא למימר? mai icha l'meimar? What can you say? It sort of
reminds us of the whole מכירת חמץ. mechiras chametz. How much is
the rental real or is it basically a ritual and like somewhat
of a farce? So if it's a real rental, I understand the
non-Jew wouldn't want to do it because he'd really be afraid that
you might take over some control. But if it's just a complete
sort of farce and ritual and so on, why won't he go
along with it? So now this allows us to discuss this debate
about what is the nature of the rental. דאתמר, d'itmar, because it
was taught. רב
חסדא אמר שכירות בריאה, Rav Chisda amar schirus bria, you need a
healthy rental, says רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. ורב ששת אמר שכירות רעועה,
v'Rav Sheshes amar schirus reu'a, you can even do a shaky rental.
מאי רעועה? mai reu'a? What does shaky mean?
ומאי בריאה? u'mai bria? What does healthy mean? אי נימא בריאה ei
neima bria פרוטה pruta או פחות משוה פרוטה. o pachos mishavei pruta.
Maybe בריאה bria means you have to give him a פרוטה, pruta,
right? The minimum coin, like a dollar, you know, it’s not even
that, a nickel. That’s, you know, just to show due consideration, so,
you know, which is important in contracts. And רעועה re'uya means you
can even give him something less than a פרוטה. pruta. So that
shows that it's just like a ritual. So the גמרא Gemara says
the interesting response of the גמרא, Gemara, מי איכא למאן דאמר מעכו"ם
פחות משוה פרוטה לא? Mi ika l'man d'amar me-akum pachos mishavei pruta
lo? Who would ever say that from a non-Jew you can't do
it with less than a פרוטה? pruta? Which is shocking, right? We're
always brought up less than a פרוטה pruta is meaningless. But the
גמרא Gemara actually understands that relating to non-Jews, actually less than a
פרוטה pruta is significant. Why? Let's take a look. והשלח רבי יצחק
ברבי יעקב בר גיורי משמיה דרבי יוחנן. Ve-ha shelach Rabi Yitzchak b'rebi
Yaakov bar Giyurei mishmei d'Rabi Yochanan. So רבי יצחק Rabi Yitzchak sent
in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. הוי יודעים, Havei yodim,
be aware, ששוכרים מן העכו"ם אפילו בפחות משוה פרוטה. she-sochrim min ha-akum
afilu b'pachos mishavei pruta. That you can rent from a non-Jew even
with less than a פרוטה. pruta. Now, maybe that's just the position
that you could do a shaky rental. How does it prove that
everybody agrees that's okay? Because here's the idea that it's consistent with.
ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. V'amar Rabi Chiya bar
Abba amar Rabi Yochanan. And said רבי חייא בר אבא Rabi Chiya
bar Abba in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. Also again
in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. בן נח נהרג על
פחות משוה פרוטה. Ben Noach neherag al pachos mishavei pruta. So we
have this idea that
any of the שבע מצות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach are
for בני נח Bnei Noach you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. You don't
have any gradations of punishment like paying back the money, מלקות, malkos,
it's all חייב מיתה. chayav misa. The other interesting idea though that
you have by בני נח Bnei Noach is that the basic idea
of שיעורים, shiurim, like minimums, don't apply. One example is this that
the גמרא Gemara is saying that even less than a פרוטה pruta
is considered גזל, gezel, which is one of the שבע מצות בני
נח, Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach, there's no minimum amount of money, and
therefore you transgress and חייב מיתה chayav misa is just what's said
by any of the שבע מצות בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach.
But another example for example would be one of the שבע מצות
בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach is like אבר מן החי. eiver
min hachai. Let's say he ate less than a כזית. kezayis. Or
here's another example which is much more relevant,
there's an איסור issur of רציחה. retzicha. Okay, according to the גמרא,
Gemara, a
בן נח Ben Noach is נהרג neherag on עוברין, ubarin, on fetuses.
A Jew is not. Now there's a whole debate of course what
is the nature of of you know of aborting fetuses for Jews,
is it do you have positions from one extreme of רב משה
Rav Moshe which is basically it's רציחה retzicha just without the sort
of court you know the חייב מיתה, chayav misa, again for Jews,
and the other extreme that basically says it's more just like you
know some type of a זרע לבטלה zera l'vatala type of an
issue of a loss of potential life but it's not you know
completely in a different category than anything like injury or רציחה retzicha
whatnot and you have all positions in between. That's for Jews. But
that's but for non-Jews even a fetus is considered רציחה. retzicha. So
there seems to be a pattern here and again you know you
could try to sort of speculate on why that in the way
חז"ל Chazal understood the nature of שבע מצות בני נח Sheva Mitzvos
Bnei Noach they understood this idea of defining minimum amounts, you know,
because if you think about it a fetus's life is a definition
of a minimum definition of life, right? So the definitions of sort
of the minimum thresholds is doesn't apply. Anything constitutes. Any amount of
stealing, any amount of אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, any amount
any degree of life is considered life. So there is that pattern
about that and again I don't know exactly how to explain why
but that is the approach that חז"ל Chazal have by שבע מצות
בני נח. Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach. So here it's saying so you
see less than a פרוטה pruta vis-a-vis non-Jews if it's true about
the שבע מצות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach, therefore what it's
saying is that when you relate to non-Jews it always is considered
you know these minimums aren't relevant and it's always considered to be
significant. Now that doesn't necessarily mean that when it comes to a
Jew renting from a non-Jew you would apply these sort of non-Jew
law rather than the Jewish law, you know that's always that's why
that's why מכירת חמץ mechiras chametz is always such a challenge because
when you sort of have an intersection of two different law legal
systems which one rules, which one sort of you know dictates. But
here the גמרא Gemara is understanding since the non-Jew's involved less than
a פרוטה pruta would be relevant. Now I tried to explain it
one minute in a sort of nice abstract way because I really
do see it as part of this pattern of not having like
minimums, but it should be noted that רש"י Rashi and others say
that it specifically has to do with how חז"ל Chazal understood sort
of like you know sort of the non-Jewish mindset. You know it's
quite funny because the stereotype of the and the stereotype is you
know that Jews are cheap, right? That's the stereotype. But according to
this understanding it's that oh Jews are very it's the non-Jews that
are cheap, Jews less than a פרוטה pruta big deal, you know
whatever מוחל mochel doesn't matter. Non-Jews even a portion of a penny
they're מקפיד makpid on. So therefore even the smallest amount of money
is significant for them and therefore it's always considered גזל gezel and
therefore if you give them something less than a פרוטה pruta it's
significant since they're on the receiving end it's significant enough for them
to therefore be willing to engage you know finalize the deal on
the basis of it. So that's how רש"י Rashi explains you know
the point of the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara of comparing the idea
of the בן נח ben Noach הלכה halacha of גזל gezel to
this issue that it would work for שכירות. sechirut. You've been trying
to say something.
Yeah, two things. One is that it's actually what רש״י Rashi says
about why converts have to learn לקט שכחה פאה ומעשר עני Leket
Shikhcha Peah Ma'aser Ani to get us in the mindset of we
don't care as much about property as the non-Jew. But
and the second thing is there's a statement in סנהדרין Sanhedrin in
the גמרא Gemara there that says that there's nothing that's permitted for
a Jew that is prohibited for a non-Jew.
Right. So they deal with those issues. That's a big- how much
is- yes that's a problem right right right right. So okay that's
a good point that right that normally we assume anything that's forbidden
for a non-Jew is equally forbidden for a Jew. All those questions,
the abortion question, all those questions are questions they're dealt with in
the ראשונים Rishonim there, yes.
It seems to me we're holding non-Jews up to a much higher
standard than Jew. You know, the תורה Torah says don't steal. So
we're telling non-Jews if you steal a bubblegum wrapper you're חייב. chayav.
Jews can steal a little bit.
Well that גזל, gezel, certainly we never said it's מותר. mutar. We
didn't say it's מותר mutar but the degree of punishment...
Right. So how we're expecting them to adhere to a very...
Yeah so you're right. So
that's- so that's a variation of Charlie's question which is that the
גמרא Gemara actually says that- that exactly that, that you know anything
that is forbidden for non-Jews should certainly be forbidden for Jews. But
then you have particularly in these areas of minimums, defining
minimums, although the broad category is equal, murder, stealing, etc., this definition
of the threshold is definitely different. One answer is yes, yes, yes,
it's equally- it's also forbidden for Jews. It's just it's not punishable.
But again okay it's a very good question and you know so
that's discussed in סנהדרין Sanhedrin because סנהדרין Sanhedrin makes the assertion where
it deals with שבע בני נח Sheva Benei Noach that you don't
have these differences and then we find out that you do have
these differences. So the ראשונים Rishonim really try to get- you know
to deal with it but the question is right on target, yes.
I mean Jews spend all this time you know figuring out exactly
what the minimum is and for- it could be that they just
want to keep it simple for the non-Jews like look any stealing
is no good.
Yeah yeah but the keep it simple as I tell my guys
you know a lot of time in אשכנזי Ashkenazi פסק psak you
get in the גמרא Gemara all these distinctions and this case is
this and this case is this and then you get to the
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and basically it's like you know what I
say is the principle of keep it simple stupid. So we'll just
say we're going to treat it all the same. Of course the
effect of treating it all the same is you're מחמיר machmir about
everything, right? So you know it's very nice that we're going to
treat it all the same and say חייב מיתה chayav mita even
in פחות משוה פרוטה. pahot mi-shaveh perutah. So it's an issue. So
let's take a look anyway. Therefore says the
גמרא, Gemara, therefore נהרג אפחות משוה פרוטה neherag apachot mishaveh perutah ולא
ניתן להשבון. ve-lo nitan le-hishavon.
And רש״י Rashi says that means that Jews have a מצוה mitzvah
to return stolen objects, non-Jews do not. תוספות Tosafot says it means
something different. תוספות Tosafot says that it means that if a non-Jew
steals- takes from a Jew less than a פרוטה perutah there's no
idea of giving it back because when the Jew is the one
losing less than a פרוטה perutah it's not an issue right because
from Jews' perspective it's not considered- they're not מקפיד makpid on it,
again let's look at it that way whereas non-Jews are מקפיד makpid
on it. Anyway, since we're assuming non-Jews it's meaningful, obviously renting less
than a פרוטה perutah would work according even if you need a
serious rental. So what's the issue of whether it's a healthy or
a shaky rental? So the גמרא Gemara says,
where are we? אלא בריאה, Ela beriah, so healthy means במוהרקי ואבורגיני,
bimuharki ve'aburgini, in מוהרקי muharki and אבורגיני. aburgini. ראועה בלא מוהרקי ואבורגיני,
Re'uah belo muharki ve'aburgini, and ראועה re'uah is without that. So what
the heck does that mean? So רש״י Rashi says these words mean
like chairs and benches. So that if it's a healthy rental it
means that I as the Jew since I rented from the non-Jew
I can fill the entire courtyard with lawn chairs or whatever and
you can't come and complain on- at least on שבת Shabbat and
say what the heck are you doing? I got to use the
courtyard, I got to use- I'm sorry, you lent- you rented it
to me, I have a right to do whatever I want. Okay
so that's what רש״י Rashi says to actually make it difficult for
the non-Jew to use, at least on שבת Shabbat you'd be entitled.
As opposed to the other position which is no no no you
don't have any real rights. You really can't do anything today that
you couldn't do yesterday. It's purely ritual and formalistic. So that's the
way רש״י Rashi explains it. תוספות Tosafot and the ערוך Aruch say
that these words mean like how much is it registered, how much
do you sort of put it in official documents and get officials
like you'd get it at what's it called like a- what do
you get- a notary public you know and that that's the issue
okay but anyway so there's one position that it's real and one
that it's very much you know
pro-forma and just a ritual. So the גמרא Gemara now says if
it's a real rental you understand why the non-Jew wouldn't want to
participate, he doesn't want to give up his right. But if it's
a completely sort of like make-believe ritual type of religious requirement how
is this going to be an obstacle? For Jews living amongst non-Jews.
Let me make sure I understood this thus far. So what we're
saying is that if it's a real rental you'd actually have to
officially notarize it?
Or maybe you, yeah,
but would we ever have to do that? In other words, if
it's just a contract, all you need is witnesses, you don't ever
need to go to the court to notarize it. Why would the
non-Jew be different? Why do they need it different than our Jews?
I don't know, it's a good point. And B, you know in
terms of like, you know, lawn chairs and all that, I mean
regardless of who I'm renting it from, doesn't mean I have necessarily
the right to obstruct it. If I rent from you, doesn't mean
I can like put all your space with lawn chairs. It means
I'm allowed to put whatever it is, but if it means that
your access is impeded, I can't do that ever, right? It doesn't
mean it's all my חצר. Chatzer.
Alright, I don't know, it's a good point. So but you know,
but maybe the point is that at least if in principle you
could do... I don't know, you're right. So what you're saying is
you could have imagined a case where it was בריאה Bria and
you didn't go this far. Fine, okay, but maybe anyway, but maybe
for the גמרא, Gemara, okay, it's a good point.
The question is what does it mean to have rights to the
חצר? Chatzer?
Exactly. Alright, so anyway let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara
says. So, the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא למאן
דאמר שכירות בריאה בעינן, Hani nicha leman de'amar sechirut bria ba'inan, if
you need a healthy one, which I take Michael's point would make
me demand or give you right which would be more than we
might otherwise say, but maybe we would want to demand that or
emphasize that in order to show that you really are like, you
know, you've really taken possession of that space, you know, maybe that's
what we would demand for הלכות עירובין. Hilchot Eruvin. So if you
would demand that, then I understand why he wouldn't want to go
along with it. אלא, Ela, by the way, Michael, you could say
since the whole point of it is to get you not to
live amongst the non-Jew, maybe that's why we would demand this type
of a rental in order to make it an obstacle. But אלא
למאן דאמר שכירות רעועה בעינן, Ela leman de'amar sechirut reu'a ba'inan, but
if all we demand is some type of a shaky type of
a pro forma type of a thing, so מאי איכא למימר, mai
icha lemeimar, why is this going to be an obstacle? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אפילו הכי, afilu hachi, even with this, חשיש עכו"ם
לכשפים, chashish akum lechshafim, he's concerned about witchcraft, ולא מוגר, velo mogir,
and he won't rent it. Now what does witchcraft mean? Your witchcraft?
So, your witchcraft. So the גמרא Gemara has self-awareness that the non-Jews
see us doing certain types of rituals and they don't know what
we're doing and they think it's witchcraft. Right. So and maybe this
is, you know, like he thinks that
you're going to use that space and maybe like, I don't know,
Scheinfeld said something like voodoo, right? Since it's something that he had
control over, so maybe it allows you to do some witchcraft against
him. But I think a better explanation is, and again I, you
know, I think it was in that article that I mentioned, it's
sort of like that's the whole point. If this whole thing isn't
a real rental and it's all just some weird religious type of
a... we've got to do this, our religion requires us to put
these little wires on top of the telephone poles and then rent
all the space. The whole thing looks like voodoo, you know, it
looks like witchcraft. What is this nonsense? So therefore he doesn't want
to be a participant. I don't know what that stuff is, it
doesn't make any sense to me, I don't want to be a
party. Okay. So anyway, so fascinating in this גמרא Gemara that the
idea of not being, of demanding, A, in the משנה Mishna maybe
not having any way of dealing with it, but even according to
the גמרא, Gemara, demanding rental from non-Jews and the whole issue is
really because of trying to create Jews living only among Jews in
this coherent courtyard and so on, and the reluctant non-Jews will have
to participate in this whole type of process.
It would just be too easy.
It would just be too easy. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay.
גופא, Gufa, let's go back to the statement we've made before. חצר
של
עובד כוכבים הרי הוא כדיר של בהמה.
Chatzer shel
oved kochavim harei hu kedir shel behema. The courtyard of a non-Jew,
again like a stable, מותר להכניס ולהוציא מן החצר לבתים ומן הבתים
לחצר. mutar lehachnis ulehotzi min hachatzer labatim umin habatim lachatzer.
So the first statement is because fundamentally their presence is not, does
not have the status of a house, you know, to create sort
of עירוב Eruv problems, you can go from the courtyard into their
houses, from their houses into the courtyard. But so what's the scenario
though? The whole משנה Mishna is that you, if, that they make
a problem. So the scenario of the first part of the משנה
Mishna is no Jew is living in the courtyard. You have a
courtyard, there's no Jews, and you're going and visiting your non-Jewish friend
on שבת, Shabbat, Shac. Okay. But you happen to be there. So
here you've got your courtyard... where are the markers?
Anyway, it doesn't matter. It doesn't matter. Whatever. I don't really need
the markers for this.
Okay, I don't need for this. Anyway, is it there? Okay. Anyway,
so here you are in your courtyard and no... everybody's searching, everybody
has dry-erase markers in their backpacks. All right, anyway, so here you
are, very impressive. Anyway, anyway look at this context. Here you are,
you have all these houses in your courtyard
and we'll do an N. Okay. Anyway, so fundamentally
it's like, it, you know, it doesn't have a status of houses
that create a mixed... a mixed domain here and a distinct domain
there and all those הלכות halachot why we need to unify the
domain, since they're non-Jews... we'll say it the nicer way, they're not
relevant to the הלכות halachot of carrying, it doesn't have that whole
sense of creating distinct domains. So therefore, here you... You are, you're
the
Jew. Anyway, if you're visiting on שבת, Shabbos, you can take stuff
inside to out and outside to in and it's all considered one
space. Okay, fundamentally this is the idea that in principle these are
not distinct spaces. And if nobody is living there, you can carry
galore in the courtyard and from the courtyard into their houses and
vice versa. However, as soon as a Jew moves in, now because
of the תקנה, takkana, because you know, in principle it's not a
problem, but because of the תקנה takkana that we don't want you
living there, now all of a sudden the whole courtyard darkens. Okay,
and now, so that shows how much in principle it isn't the
problem and it's based on the תקנה. takkana. Okay, so let's take
a look.
Is the courtyard itself not considered its own space? Like if I'm
coming from...
You can carry within the courtyard stuff that started in the courtyard,
but you can't carry from the courtyard to the houses or the
houses to the courtyard. Okay, so now it says like this: So
let's see that again. חצר של עכו״ם הרי הוא כדיר של בהמה
מותר להכניס ולהוציא ממנו לבתים ומבתים לחצר. Chatzer shel akkum harei hu
k'dir shel beheima mutar l'hachnis v'l'hotzi mimenu l'batim u'mibatim l'chatzer. Right,
the basic issue of עירוב Eruv is yes, you can carry within
one house and you can carry within the courtyard things that start
in the courtyard, but you can't carry from something outside of the
courtyard into, from the house to the courtyard, the courtyard to the
house. Okay, now, so therefore if you're just, if you're not living
there, it's all fine. ואם יש שם ישראל אחד, V'im yesh sham
Yisrael echad, but as soon as one Jew moves in, like one
Jew moves in, he ruins the neighborhood. So one Jew moves in,
so אוסר, oser, then
he makes it forbidden to carry again, you know, from the courtyard
into the houses and so on. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir,
this is what Rabbi Meir says. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר לעולם
אינו אוסר עד שיהיו שני ישראלים אוסרים זה על זה, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov omer l'olam eino oser ad she'yehu shnei Yisraelim osrim zeh
al zeh, until there are two Jews, then they make it forbidden
one on the other, then they create all the problems, but one
Jew is not going to be a problem, quite ironically for the
reasons we said before. Okay, now we're going to try to understand
this piece by piece. אמר מר. Amar Mar. חצר של עכו״ם הרי
הוא כדיר של בהמה. Chatzer shel akkum harei hu k'dir shel beheima.
So, right, if there's only non-Jews there's not a problem. והנן תנן,
V'anan tnan, our משנה Mishna says: הדר עם עכו״ם בחצר הרי זה
אוסר עליו, Hadar im akkum b'chatzer harei zeh oser alav, that somebody
who lives with the non-Jew, then the non-Jew makes it forbidden to
him. Now what's the problem? I just explained to you the difference
is: is a Jew living in the courtyard or not living in
the courtyard? So רש״י Rashi says it's a different set you want
to pick up, it's going about the second line in the משנה.
Mishna. Who is making it forbidden to whom? Our משנה Mishna says
if you're with the non-Jew, right, הרי זה אוסר עליו, harei zeh
oser alav, the non-Jew makes it forbidden on you. That's the way
it means it, therefore on you, but wait, both are true. As
soon as you're living here, okay, what's the הלכה? halacha? I lost
my eraser. Anyway, what's my הלכה? halacha? As soon as you are
living here, you're the Jew and you're living here, okay, you cannot
take from your house to the courtyard and the courtyard to your
house, and also they can't, you know, can they take from the
courtyard to their house or their house to the courtyard? They don't,
they, and you take something into their houses and out of their
houses. So for, so if he is, if you're living together and
you're restricted, then the non-Jew is אוסר עליו. oser alav. He makes
it, he makes you, it's forbidden for you to do what you
want to do. Okay, if you can't now take into his house,
you are אוסר, oser, you are making it forbidden not for him,
he's not relevant, but you are making his house off limits. Okay,
so you would assume it's both are true. If there's a problem,
it's a problem both ways. But the גמרא Gemara understands, at least,
that that's not true, that the משנה Mishna says, our משנה Mishna
says that הרי זה אוסר עליו, harei zeh oser alav, which according
to רש״י Rashi means, you know, that the non-Jew makes it forbidden
to you, whereas the ברייתא Baraisa says ואם יש שם ישראל אחד
אוסר, v'im yesh sham Yisrael echad oser, so it sounds like the
ישראל Yisrael is אוסר oser and he makes it forbidden vis-a-vis the
non-Jew's house. Okay, so what is the story? Let's take a look.
So yes, the assumption is clearly that the non-Jew occupies a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid and there is no doubt about that, right? The
non-Jew's in his house, the house is considered רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
Right, right, right. Look, four walls is always a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, you know.
I mean, the רמב״ן, Ramban, as we mentioned before by רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, discusses if ownership, real ownership, matters in defining those רשויות.
reshuyos. And even he was emphasizing the idea of, it's relevant for
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but he
might say the same for רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But anyway, for
most, the ownership
is not relevant, but you could have a הפקר hefker place surrounded
by walls. Okay, so anyway, so it says, ah, so that's the
גמרא's Gemara question, that the ברייתא Baraisa makes it sound like you
make it forbidden for him, but not that he makes it forbidden
for you. והנן תנן, V'anan tnan, הדר עם עכו״ם בחצר הרי זה
אוסר עליו, hadar im akkum b'chatzer harei zeh oser alav, which understands
again somehow, you could have read it either way, but anyway, the
non-Jew makes it forbidden on you. So לא קשיא, lo kashya, says
the גמרא, Gemara, הא דאיתא הא דליתא. ha d'isa ha d'leisa. It
matters whether the non-Jew is living there or not. Okay, somehow it's
understood as soon as you move in, then you cannot move
stuff in and out of his house. but whether he makes it
restricted to you, he has that impact on you, it's only when
he actually has a real presence. Not that he owns a house
in the courtyard, but there actually is a non-Jew living in the
courtyard. That then makes it restricts your movement in and out of
your house. Again, if you understand that this whole thing is because
of a תקנה takana and not wanting Jews to live amongst non-Jews,
so if the non-Jew isn't there, the most restrictive is when we
say he is אוסר עליו. oser alav. How often or whatever, it's
less that you're going to want to take in and out of
his house, you're going to want to take in and out of
your house. So the more restrictive scenario is him אוסר עליו, oser
alav, and the גמרא Gemara is saying that that's only when they're
actually living there. If they're not in their houses and no non-Jew
is in their house, it's not a problem, because let's face it,
if it's a תקנה takana issue and about living among them, you
understand why that is less problematic. So this, which is the most
restrictive, we're going to limit to when they're actually living in their
houses. So let's read a little bit further, okay? So הא דאיתא
הא דליתא. ha d'isa ha d'leisa. Matters if he's in his house
or not. ומאי קסבר, u'mai kasavar, what do you hold? אי קסבר
דירה בלא בעלים שמה דירה. ei kasavar dira belo baalim shema dira.
I tried to explain it in a תקנה takana way, but here
the גמרא, Gemara, although recognizing this whole thing is a תקנה takana
or by the way explaining it, here is going back to more
formal categories. If you think that a house without anybody living in
it constitutes a house, אפילו עכו״ם נמי נאסר. afillu akum nami ne'esar.
So therefore then even, so then even if, אפילו, afillu, then even
עכו״ם, akum, wait a minute, then even the non-Jew, אפילו עכו״ם, afillu
akum, then even the non-Jew
should be forbidden.
One minute. Does that, wait a minute, that means that he's אוסר
oser on you, if he's not there. Right, so that's the question,
meaning we're saying that if he's there he's אוסר oser on you,
but if he's not there, you're always אוסר עליו. oser alav. So,
hold on a minute. אי קסבר דירה בלא בעלים שמה דירה אפילו
עכו״ם נמי נאסר. ei kasavar dira belo baalim shema dira afillu akum
nami ne'esar. If he's not living there and it's a דירה dira
and
it's אוסר oser on you. So if it's considered a דירה, dira,
it makes no difference if he's there or not, he's always just
אוסר. oser. I understand, I just don't understand how it fits
in the phrase of אפילו עכו״ם. afillu akum. What does it mean,
אפילו עכו״ם? afillu akum? It should mean even if he's not
there, it should be אוסר oser on you. Okay, let's
keep on reading. What if even when he's not there it's
considered a domicile, then it should be that even when he's not
there it should
be forbidden on you. I don't understand the phrase אפילו עכו״ם. afillu
akum. ואי קסבר דירה בלא בעלים לא שמה דירה, v'ei kasavar dira
belo baalim lo shema dira, and if it doesn't, and if when
he's not there it's not, then אפילו ישראל נמי לא נאסר. afillu
Yisrael nami lo ne'esar. No, wait one minute. If he's not there,
then he's not אוסר עליו. oser alav. What? If it's considered a
דירה dira even when it's empty and it is אוסר oser on
you, so it's certainly considered a דירה dira when he is not
there. When he's not there, we're saying that he's not אוסר עליו,
oser alav, okay, but you are still, so you can carry, but
he still can't carry. Right, that's the point. If he's not there,
we're saying you can carry but he still can't carry. Okay, so
presumably, you can't carry in and out of his house. Okay, so
let's do it again. So, one minute, let's do this again. אי
קסבר דירה בלא בעלים שמה דירה, ei kasavar dira belo baalim shema
dira, so if his presence creates an issue, then אפילו עכו״ם נמי
נאסר. afillu akum nami ne'esar. ואי קסבר דירה בלא בעלים לא שמה
דירה, v'ei kasavar dira belo baalim lo shema dira, if it's not
an issue, אפילו ישראל נמי לא נאסר. afillu Yisrael nami lo ne'esar.
I'm still not getting this. I'm sorry, it made sense when I
did this last night. Do any of your translations help? What does
Rabbi Meir hold? If he holds that a residence without its owners
is still considered a residence and it is prohibited to carry in
the courtyard even when the owner is away, then even a Gentile
in absentia should likewise prohibit for carrying. A Gentile in absentia, so
whenever it says אפילו עכו״ם נמי נאסר afillu akum nami ne'esar just
means even when he's not around. Even when he's not around, okay.
Okay. And what does it say about the next phrase? And if
he holds that a residence without its owner is not considered residence,
then even a Jew who is away should also not prohibit for
carrying. Oh, even when a Jew is not... when even when a
Jew is away, he'd not also prohibit for carrying. Oh, okay, okay,
okay. Oh, I got it. That was... okay, okay, okay. I got
it. I got it. Fine. Okay. Let's try that again. All right.
Let's try that again. Okay. ומאי קסבר. Umai kasavar. Okay. So... okay.
אי קסבר דירה בלא בעלים שמה דירה, Ei kasavar dirah belo bealim
shemah dirah, if you hold that it's still considered a house even
if nobody's living there, אפילו עכום נמי נאסר, afillu Akum nami neesar,
though in the case where the non-Jew is away, why is it
okay? It should still create a problem on the Jew. That we
got. But here's... but the other line is ואי קסבר דירה בלא
בעלים לא שמה דירה, ve-ei kasavar dirah belo bealim lo shemah dirah,
and if when you're not there it has no impact, אפילו ישראל
נמי לא נאסר, afillu Yisrael nami lo neesar, we know that when
Jews aren't home—right, that's the part I was getting at—we... if we
knew...
we know when Jews are...
forget the case of non-Jews. Five
Jews live in a courtyard. If four of them aren't home, you
still have to make an עירוב. Eruv. So... so that's basically an
easier way to say it. When... with the case of Jews, we
know that even if you're not home, they create a problem and
you have to make an עירוב. Eruv. So how come in this
case when the non-Jew isn't home, it makes things better? That's the
easier way to say it. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. The גמרא Gemara says like this. לעולם קסבר דירה בלא בעלים
לא שמה דירה. Le-olam kasavar dirah belo bealim lo shemah dirah. You
know what? Really, when you're not home, fundamentally it's not a problem.
So therefore, so why then is it an issue when a Jew
is not home that you have to make an עירוב Eruv with
his רשות? reshut? ישראל דכי איתא אסר, Yisrael de-chi ita assar, but
a Jew who when he is home actually really creates a real
problem, כי ליתא גזרו ביה רבנן, ki leita gazru bei rabanan, when
he's not home the rabbis actually, you know, you know, said, 'Okay,
we still have to do it anyway.' עכום דכי איתא גזירה שמא
ילמדו ממעשיו, Akum de-chi ita gezeirah shemah yilmedu mimaasav, but the non-Jew
who we know that the whole thing is a תקנה takanah and
that even when he's home it's only because of this concern of
dwelling among them, דכי איתא אסר, de-chi ita assar, we only made
a problem when he was home. דכי ליתא לא אסר, De-chi leita
lo assar, we didn't make a problem when he wasn't home. Okay.
So that's like I first explained it to you, that the basic
point is this whole thing is a גזירה. gezeirah. Since the whole
thing is a גזירה, gezeirah, we're going to make a bigger deal
about it when he's home than when he's not home because the
whole point is a concern of
living among them. Among Jews, that the whole thing is a real
issue about making an עירוב, Eruv, then even when they're not home
it's going to be a problem. Okay. So that's the way it
says. When Jews... is not home, Jews... the whole thing is the
real... the main... so even when they're not home it's a problem.
By non-Jews, it's more of this concern and this גזירה gezeirah of
living among them, and therefore we're only making an issue... a bigger
issue when they are home. So why on the minute the גמרא
Gemara says והתנן, Ve-hatnan, but didn't we... דכי ליתא לא אסר. De-chi
leita lo assar. דכי ליתא לא אסר, De-chi leita lo assar, you're
telling me really if a non-Jew is not there, it's not a
problem? He doesn't make it restricted on the Jew? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, המניח את ביתו והלך לו לשבות בעיר
אחרת, ha-maniach et beito ve-halach lo lishbot be-ir acheret, if somebody leaves
his house and goes to spend שבת Shabbat in another city, אחד
עכום ואחד ישראל אוסר דברי רבי מאיר, echad Akum ve-echad Yisrael oser
divrei Rabbi Meir, still makes it forbidden. So even when the non-Jew
isn't home, there's still going to be restriction of carrying in the
courtyard. The גמרא Gemara says, no. התם דאתי ביומיה. Hatam de-ati beyomei.
That's when he's not so far away and he might... and he
might be able to come back in the same day. So since
it's possible he'll be around שבת, Shabbat, we still consider it as
if he is present. But if he literally has gone like to,
you know, far away, then it is not an issue. So what
the גמרא Gemara said until this point is, again, none of this
is in the משנה. Mishnah. משנה Mishnah says if a non-Jew is
there, it doesn't suggest any solution, you're stuck. The גמרא Gemara says
actually you can do שכירות. sechirut. So A gives you an option
which is interesting, and B, it explains why, and it explains it's
not a formal issue at all about, you know, what defines a
unification or not, what defines an עירוב. Eruv. It's all because we
want to do a policy and not have you live among them.
And therefore we're making it difficult and we're demanding you do שכירות,
sechirut, and that allows רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to say the paradoxical
point that two is worse than one because it's a more common
case. And because the whole thing is this שכירות sechirut issue... is
this more גזירה gezeirah issue, we're able to say that even though
by Jews when they're not home it's an issue, by non-Jews if
they're not home, it will not be an issue, they will not
make it restricted for you. Yes? I just one of them not
understanding. If, you know, we're saying we really don't want you living
with the non-Jew, so therefore we said עירובי חצרות Eruvei Chatzerot is
too easy, let's do what's hard. So therefore, you know... so
we should make everything hard. Why do we even make not living
there? Right, exactly. Or why doesn't שכירות sechirut work either? Just... I
understand. I understand. I don't know the answer. You know, the point
is that so much of this is the גמרא's, Gemara you know,
sort of reading into these earlier sources because that whole idea that
the whole thing is a policy issue is not in any of
these sources. It's the whole... it's the explanation the גמרא Gemara is
introducing into it. Okay. Let's now continue on the גמרא. Gemara. But
that's the basic take, that it's a policy issue and it's a
bigger issue when the non-Jews are actually living there than when they...
than they own the property but they're not living there. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. והתנן... Ve-hatnan... I just read that.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halachah ke-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We rule like
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, which is a leniency,
right? It's only... problem with two Jews. We always rule... Right. Well,
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. רב הונא אמר
מנהג. Rav Huna amar minhag. No, the מנהג minhag is like רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
which basically means רש״י Rashi says the difference is we don't go
ahead and make a big public announcement
about it, but if anybody asks a שאלה shaila that's how we
פסקן. pasken. Understand it's acceptable. Right, so רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov. רבי יוחנן אמר נהגו Rabbi Yochanan amar nahagu as
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
It's not like, it's like
that's how the people are practicing. We would actually prefer the other
פסק, psak, but that's what the people
are practicing, so if people do it, if you ask me a
שאלה shaila I'll tell you we rule against it, but if you're
actually going and doing it I'm not going to say anything because
that's the accepted practice.
What's the exact difference between מנהג minhag and נהגו? nahagu?
So that's what I said, מנהג minhag means according
to רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot based on another גמרא, Gemara, that
it's actually the way we פסקן, pasken, but we don't necessarily go
out of our way to publicize it. But if anybody asks a
שאלה, shaila, that's how I'll פסקן. pasken. Whereas נהגו nahagu means actually
I personally פסקן pasken otherwise, but because everybody is doing it I'm
not going to say anything. So the people changed the הלכה halacha
or they well change well there is always this dialectic between practice
and הלכה. halacha. Here it's a more subtle change because
if you actually ask me a פסק psak I'll say it's אסור,
assur, but I'm not going to go proactively and try to change
it. I'm going to be okay with it. I'll leave it and
be okay with it. Yes, it's become accepted practice.
Basically, yes, that's what the נהגו nahagu is. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף. Amar lei
Abaye le-Rav Yosef. So now אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, קיימא לן, kaima lan, look we generally hold anyway, משנת רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב קב ונקי, mishnat Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov kav ve-naki,
that the teaching of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
is like a sifted measure of grain, meaning he doesn't say too
much but when he says it it's very, you know, precise and
very, you know, authoritative.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Va-amar Rav
Yehuda
amar Shmuel, so in
general we tend to
go like רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב.
Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Va-amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel and not
only that, Rav Yehuda says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה
כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב. halacha ke-Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We rule like
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. So מהו לאורויי במקום
רבו? mahu le-oruyei be-makom rabbo? So since it's so well accepted, although
as we saw not everybody agrees, some just said נהגו nahagu or
מנהג, minhag, but he says look, it seems pretty clear, black and
white that
that's the הלכה. halacha. We normally go by him. שמואל Shmuel says
we go like him. You could also
throw in, which is what of course רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
throw in, הלכה כדברי המקל בעירוב. halacha ke-divrei ha-meikel be-eruv. So if
it's so black and white, am I
allowed to פסקן pasken it even in the presence of my רבי?
rebbe?
So this gets us, going to get us into a whole
other conversation, the problem about פסקן paskening in front of your רבי.
rebbe. What's considered to be פסקן, paskening, right? If somebody tells me
can I strike a match on שבת, Shabbos, can I
say oh well you know my רבי rebbe is around I can't
פסקן pasken that? Yeah. So at what stage is it considered to
be פסקן paskening or not? So he says can you פסקן pasken
this in the presence of your רבי? rebbe? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, אפילו ביעתא בכותחא,
afilu be'ata be-kutcha, even eating an egg in a בכותחא, kutcha, in
a milk dip, בעו מיניה מרב חסדא, ba'u minei mi-Rav Chisda, the
students would ask רב חסדא Rav Chisda if you could do it.
רש״י Rashi said like to test to see what he would say,
you know even though his רבי rebbe was around. So there is
so רש״י Rashi says no problem, it's like a קלוץ קשיא. klotz
kashya. Okay, I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says in a minute.
They asked him can you eat an egg with cheese? So they
asked him כל שני דרב הונא, kol shenei de-Rav Huna, as long
as all the years that רב הונא Rav Huna was alive, who
was רב חסדא's Rav Chisda רבי, rebbe, ולא אורי ve-lo ori and
he refused to פסקן. pasken. So basically even if something is yeah
is stupid and black and white, you can't פסקן pasken it in
the presence of your רבי. rebbe. אמר ליה רב יעקב בר אבא
לאביי. Amar lei Rav Yaakov bar Abba le-Abaye. I'll talk about this
in a minute but let's just read the cases. So said רב
יעקב בר אבא Rav Yaakov bar Abba to אביי, Abaye, כגון מגילת
תענית. kegon Megillat Taanit. How about מגילת תענית? Megillat Taanit? You know,
we have a book, it says you can fast on this day,
you can't fast on this way, you can say הספדים hespedim on
this day, you can't say it on that day. And I say
to you like can I say הספד hesped today? Can I fast
today? So it's in a book, right? It's like I ask you
basically, even if you're saying like let's say it's a black and
white שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, can I tell you that it's what's
in the שולחן ערוך? Shulchan Aruch? You know, is that פסקן? paskening?
It's right there. So it says how about that? דכתיבא ומנחא, de-ketiva
u-mancha, it's written and it's on the shelf. מהו לאורויי באתרא דרביה,
mahu le-oruyei be-atra de-rabbeih, can you give a פסק psak in the
presence of your רבי rebbe and tell him what באתרא דרביה? be-atra
de-rabbeih? באתרא Be-atra means like you know the place. Well we'll discuss
what the place means, okay? The city, right? It doesn't necessarily even
mean that he's in the room, right? It just means his location,
his right, his city. So that's correct, we'll talk about that. So
anyway, is that considered פסקן? paskening? I'm just telling you what it
says in the book. אמר ליה, Amar lei, הכי אמר רב יוסף,
hachi amar Rav Yosef, here's what רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, אפילו
ביעתא בכותחא בעו מיניה מרב חסדא כל שני דרב הונא ולא אורי.
afilu be'ata be-kutcha ba'u minei mi-Rav Chisda kol shenei de-Rav Huna ve-lo
ori. Even you know they even asked him about an egg in
milk and he refused to פסקן. pasken. You can't פסקן pasken anything.
Now we're going to discuss more about this, but the way it
sounds now is like okay you can't say word one, right? I
mean my god black and white and so on. Comes along תוספות
Tosafot and immediately qualifies all of these statements. Okay? So let's talk
about how he qualifies. The first thing, actually I'll go in reverse
order, one of the things תוספות Tosafot says is he cannot believe
that you cannot say something is אסור. assur. If somebody comes to
me and says, right, like can I I don't know strike a
match on שבת? Shabbos? Okay, let's even ignore the fact that it's
obvious. I say oh I can't tell you, you have to ask
my רבי. rebbe. So basically you know he might go ahead and
the thing and go ahead and strike the match, right? So actually
תוספות Tosafot says to פסקן pasken something is אסור assur when somebody
you know and now presume if I maybe knew that there is
no question he's not going to do thing one until he gets
the answer, fine. But if I knew that there was a possibility
that without giving a פסק psak he might actually do something that
I know is אסור, assur, then of course I can step in
and tell him it's אסור assur to stop him from doing an
איסור. issur. That's point one תוספות Tosafos says. Point two תוספות Tosafos
says is that if he's not asking me, if somebody comes to
me in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and says, what do you
think is the הלכה halacha about I don't know using those electric
keycards on שבת Shabbos or something like that? Okay, and I say,
well, you know, I think blah blah blah blah blah. Okay, so
you're not actually telling me that you're asking for a שאלה shaila
for yourself, you're asking it more as a hypothetical, now as we
know a lot of people ask hypotheticals like were I to ask
you what would you say. But תוספות Tosafos says if it's a
hypothetical and then you're asking my halachic sort of you know it's
more like תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah than פסק psak even though the
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is in the form of how would I
פסקן pasken that I'm also allowed to say. Okay, it's only when
you're asking for a real פסק. psak. And then תוספות Tosafos says
even there תוספות Tosafos says against the פשט pshat of the גמרא
Gemara it has to be something that's a real חידוש. chiddush. So
what about the גמרא Gemara about the egg in the milk? תוספות
Tosafos says no no we don't just mean an egg in the
milk that's stupid. We mean you שחט-ed shecht a chicken and you
found the egg still in the chicken. So the question is, is
the egg פליישיג fleishig or not? How about the issue about מגילת
תענית? Megillas Taanis? So he says also it's some type of an
issue that was not black and white in terms of what you
know what that הלכה halacha actually actually means. But תוספות Tosafos actually
says that there needs to be some חידוש chiddush against what the
גמרא Gemara seems to be saying. Right, so it's okay, so it
says you know it's it's somewhat clear or maybe there's an accepted
practice about it. But תוספות Tosafos basically says there needs to be
some חידוש. chiddush. So we'll continue with this tomorrow to discuss this
issue about what exactly is forbidden and permissible especially nowadays that so
much of it is written and in the books and so on,
and what exactly is the nature of the problem about doing it
במקום רב bimkom rav about the issue of כבוד רב kvod rav
and if that's the issue then how exactly does it play out
what type of a פסק psak might be considered to be an
infringement on the issue of כבוד רב. kvod rav. So we'll see
more of this tomorrow.